<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="Plugins">
	<title>Plugin scriptlets
		<indexterm>
			<primary>plugin scriptlets</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>WinMerge plugin scriptlets</primary>
		</indexterm>
	</title>
	<para>
		Plugin scriptlets offer a way to extend some aspects of WinMerge functionality.
		WinMerge gets aware of them by means of <wordasword>plugin monikers</wordasword>,
		which it reads from a localized <filename>ini</filename> file in subfolder <filename>PluginMonikers</filename>.
		At the time of this writing, localization of plugin monikers is far from being complete. If no <filename>ini</filename>
		file exists for your preferred language, plugin monikers are read from <filename>English.ini</filename>.
	</para>
	<section>
		<title>Editor scriptlets
			<indexterm>
				<primary>editor scriptlets</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>WinMerge editor scriptlets</primary>
			</indexterm>
		</title>
		<para>Editor scriptlets distributed with WinMerge reside in subfolder
			<filename>EditorScripts</filename> within the WinMerge program folder.
			Functions implemented through editor scripts show up as additional
			commands in the file compare window's context menu.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>File transform scriptlets
			<indexterm>
				<primary>file transform scriptlets</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>WinMerge file transform scriptlets</primary>
			</indexterm>
		</title>
		<para>
			File transform scriptlets distributed with WinMerge reside in subfolder
			<filename>FileTransforms</filename> within the WinMerge program folder.
			File transforms show up as additional <guilabel>Compare As</guilabel>
			options both in the <guilabel>Select Files or Folders</guilabel> dialog
			and in the folder compare window's context menu.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Typical tasks addressed by file transforms</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Preprocess the content of text files
					</para>
					<para>
					As an example, <filename>LinesNumbered.wsc</filename> serves the very simple task of adding line numbers.
					While this may sound useless in first place, it does come in handy when you need a strict line-by-line
					comparison. The line numbers prevent WinMerge from realigning lines to yield better matches.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Extract textual content from binary files
					</para>
					<para>
					An example is <filename>xdoc2txt.wsc</filename>, which pipes files through
					<ulink url="http://ebstudio.info/home/xdoc2txt.html">xdoc2txt</ulink>,
					enabling WinMerge to compare the textual content of a large variety of office-type documents.
					Thanks to cecilyen for suggesting the use of xdoc2txt in WinMerge Open Discussion forum.
					(As a historical note, the
					<ulink url='http://freemind.s57.xrea.com/xdocdiffPlugin/en/index.html'>xDocDiff plugin</ulink>
					demonstrates the impressively impressive amount of programmatic effort that has to be taken
					to do the same thing with WinMerge&#160;2.)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Summarize meta information about files
					</para>
					<para>
					An examle is <filename>MediaInfo.wsc</filename>, which employs
					<ulink url="http://mediainfo.sourceforge.net">MediaInfo</ulink>
					to collect various properties of common media file formats.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Steps to get xdoc2txt and MediaInfo operational</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>
				Obtain a copy of <ulink url="http://shortlinks.de/n6xi">xd2tx*.zip</ulink>, and extract it into a folder of your choice.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>
				Start WinMerge, invoke
				<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Options</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
				from the menu,
				go to page <guilabel>System</guilabel>, and look for the <guilabel>Supplement folder</guilabel>.
				In this folder, look for a file named <filename>Supplement.ini</filename>.
				In section <code>Environment</code>, edit item <code>xdoc2txt</code> to reflect the folder where the <filename>xdoc2txt.exe</filename> resides.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>
				Do likewise to tell WinMerge where to find the command line version of
				<ulink url="http://mediainfo.sourceforge.net/en/Download/Windows">MediaInfo</ulink>.
				Be sure to obtain the CLI version, not the GUI one.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Associating file transforms with filename extensions</title>
			<para>
			<guilabel>Compare As</guilabel> option <guilabel>Tell from filename extension</guilabel>
			tells WinMerge to select a file transform based on the filename extension.
			The selection is done as per the rules defined in section <code>FileTransforms</code>
			of the <filename>Supplement.ini</filename> file. See preceding section on how to locate this file.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Extending the set of available plugin scriptlets</title>
		<para>
			With moderate VBScript knowledge, it is easy to figure out how to extend the set of available plugin scriptlets by looking at
			the files in subfolders <filename>FileTransforms</filename>, <filename>EditorScripts</filename>, and <filename>PluginMonikers</filename>.
			It is however a good idea to keep your extensions separate from the WinMerge program folder so they won't get lost when moving to a new version.
			You can do so by creating corresponding subfolders in the above mentioned Supplement folder, and adding a set of <filename>ini</filename>
			files as found in the primary <filename>PluginMonikers</filename> folder to your supplementary <filename>PluginMonikers</filename> folder.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <filename>ini</filename> files in the supplementary <filename>PluginMonikers</filename> folder should not repeat the
			items contained in the primary <filename>PluginMonikers</filename> folder, because WinMerge automatically combines both of them.
		</para>
		<para>
			Plugin monikers for scriptlets in the supplementary <filename>FileTransforms</filename> or <filename>EditorScripts</filename> folder
			must include the <envar>%SupplementFolder%</envar> placeholder, like in <code>script:%SupplementFolder%\EditorScripts\DoMagic.wsc</code>.
			<envar>%SupplementFolder%</envar> refers to a process-level environment variable. Plugin monikers can just as well refer to
			other environment variables.
		</para>
	</section>
</article>
